Take care of us . Protect us ...
Guide us . Use us ...
Use our hands , use our feet ...
Come to us . Come .
Fill us . Come to us ...
Hear through us . Speak through us ...
See through us . Come to us ...
Wear no badges . Dark suits , nothing shiny .
Dark , not black .
Impeccable white shirts . Windsor tie knot , double .
You must look flawless .
Remember , you are heroes . Not victims .
Under no circumstance lower your head .
If the general goes down , we are next ...
At our age , any punishment is a life sentence .
Age has turned you into a coward .
My pleasure . - thank you .
Thanks for everything ! by all means , anytime .
My respect to you . - thank you .
Thanks for coming .
- Do you want to sleep in my bed ? - No , it 's too hot .
Why do people say bad things about my grandpa ?
Your friends say bad things about him ?
No . On the Internet .
In the name of the father , the son , and the holy spirit ...
Grandparents , old spirits , accept this light as an offering .
We pray for Don Enrique , his family and this house .
We offer this light so that all e vi / leaves this place .
For everything to go well
we beg for protection for all .
We pray with all our heart .
Letona !
Don Enrique ! It 's me , valeriana !
Valeriana ! Take his gun away !
Enrique ! What the hell are you doing ?
You heard that woman crying !
Yes , you heard her weeping !
- Give me the gun ! - General , let her go .
It 's valeriana .
Search the rooms !
- The guerrilla has a spy in the house ! - Letona , take the gun away !
Okay , general . Let her go .
It is an order !
Did someone hear a woman cry ?
Are you sure ?
It was a nightmare , that 's all .
Someone sneaked into the house . I heard her .
It was her .
Did he hear her far or near ?
Close to his ear .
Then she is not near .
Shut up /
what are they saying ? - nothing .
He 's getting old . That 's what is going on .
Give me the gun .
For everyone 's sake , I can 't let you keep this .
We need to call a carpenter .
Your poor dad .
After everything that he 's gone through ,
no wonder he 's going crazy .
Stress hastens Alzheimer 's .
He 's still good at shooting . He almost got you .
He could 've killed me .
He 'll get better after the verdict .
Dona Carmen , all the servants want to leave .
Valeriana , please , tell them that this is not the right moment .
My mother needs help with my father . You all saw how ill he is .
You can 't just go and leave her all alone .
Besides , my parents have given you a home , food , a good pay .
They treat you like family . They even buy tortillas for you .
No one else is going to treat you like they do .
Think about it , please . We are going through difficult times .
They are afraid .
They are ungrateful .
Letona , please get the car ready . It 's getting late .
We ' re ready , doctor .
Dona Carmen , before leaving , they want their benefits .
Nobody else will hire you .
Is Enrique ready ?
The guerrilla fled when they heard the army was near .
I didn 't see it coming .
When I saw the fire , I grabbed my children and ran .
Violence came so abruptly .
First they set our crops on fire ,
then our homes , our clothes , and our cattle .
They separated the women and the children from the few men that were still there .
We were raped ...
And then the killings began .
Silence !
Some of us managed to run to the mountains .
Clouds protected us up there every time the helicopters were looking for us .
But there was no food , so we had to go down .
That 's when they caught me and took me to the military base .
The soldiers had their way with me . And it wasn 'tjust me .
We didn 't do anything . We were in our homes .
I 'm not embarrassed to tell you what I went through .
I hope you are not embarrassed to do justice .
That 's all , your honor .
Thank you , witness 82 .
The trial is in its second month now .
General monteverde claims that during his mandate ,
entire communities were part of the guerrilla .
All were insurgents .
According to the defense , no civilians were killed ,
only armed guerrilla members .
The general insists there was no genocide .
On the other hand , the victims ' defense calls the general ...
- Your tea , doctor . - - ... A genocidal murderer .
They remind us that , between 1982 and 1983 ,
the national army killed an average of 3,000 persons per month ,
equal to one-third of the mayan-ixil people .
According to the prosecutor , the army tried to annihilate them
to take over their lands in the oil region in the northern area of the country .
Let 's go in .
The general stated in several interviews that ...
" People are to the guerrilla as water to fish :
If you have to get rid of the fish , first you have to get rid of the water . "
He is known around the world
as one of the bloodiest dictators of Latin America .
Doctor monteverde ! Give me two minutes ...
General Enrique monteverde ...
Never signed ,
never proposed ,
never ordered the Guatemalan army to attack a specific race ,
ethnic group , or any religious group .
And that 's why there was no genocide in Guatemala .
I give the floor to his excellency , general Enrique monteverde .
Your honor ,
I know how important this trial is ...
And that Guatemala deserves respect .
But you know well
that my intention was to create a national identity ...
- - Murderer ! - In this country .
Silence , please .
I plead not guilty .
I don 't know what I am being accused of .
The Attorney General presented evidence ,
witnesses , expertise and official army documents
in which all the mayan-ixil people were considered state enemies .
Thirty-eight percent of all victims were children under twelve years old .
The harm done surpasses all human understanding .
And it has deeply damaged not only the direct victims of the massacres ,
but also the whole social fabric of Guatemala .
Telling the truth helps heal all wounds from the past .
Considering that general Enrique monteverde was aware
of the killings happening under his command ,
and did nothing to prevent them , despite being able to do so ...
He is found ...
Guilty of genocide !
Everybody , please !
Don 't talk . Say nothing .
Please , security !
Excuse me !
Take him to a hospital !
He needs a hospital !
You have to know there are thousands of people out there
wrl / ing to give false testimony for some money .
Where does this money come from ? Ask yourselves .
From your taxes !
What do you think about the judge is performance ?
She is a criminal . I wrl / send her to jarl .
Everything is okay , but I have to get rid of your cigarette .
I 'm sure heaven sent an angel to care for me .
Thank you .
Did dad tell you everything ?
You think he did all that ? Or he just gave orders ?
You believe those prostitutes more than your own father ?
Which prostitutes ?
Those Indians that paraded themselves at the trial .
They are whores , paid to lie .
Mom ! I don 't believe anybody is capable of making up such things .
You have to go through them to tell them like that .
Your dad told me they came to offer themselves at the military base .
Some were even nursing their babies .
The generals kindly offered them cleaning jobs .
But the low rank soldiers used them as their whores .
I remember every time dad left for the base , you argued ...
You cried because they had other women there .
Of course . Even generals are men .
- I don 't mean just that - - those women were there to tempt them .
I don 't mean just that . I mean everything else ...
Which side are you on ?
Don 't tell me you believe those communists .
Don 't mix things up .
When did you turn into a lefty ?
Whom have you been seeing again ?
They already convinced you .
I just want to know if you know what happened .
We must move on for the country to move fonnard .
What 's in the past , is in the past .
If we look back , we will turn into salt statues .
I know what you are thinking . I forbid you to think that .
We are r 'n front of the military hospital ,
where general monte verde has been hospitalized for over a week .
The constitutional court annulled the trial against the former dictator .
Representatives from the private sector praised the courts decision ,
insisting that it was not possible to prove that there was a genocide .
General monte verde could be released this very afternoon .
The international community has reacted negatively at the news ,
por 'nting at the corruption and rmpunity problems in the country .
Give me five minutes with the doctor . It 's just a short interview .
This isn 't the right time . We 'll negotiate later .
- Don 't let her in . - My interview . You promised !
Doctor monteverde ! Let 's talk about the father of your daughter .
How long has he been missing ? Do you know where he is ?
Don 't go there . Mind your own business , understood ?
250 meters ... General , your cigarette , please .
Let 's put your bulletproof vest on .
Don 't talk to the press . Walk straight in , please .
- 100 meters . - Ready , sir .
- Be alert , please . - Yes , sir .
Fifty meters .
Everything is under control . Don 't worry .
Be alert ! Get out of the car on my command .
Understood ?
Calm down . It 's a peaceful demonstration . Peaceful .
Why did they let so many people go through ?
We need more people . Call for help , we need backup .
Get us closer ! We have to move further !
We 're about to get out . Alpha , clear the door !
- It 's not that peaceful , sir ! - We are going out !
One , two , three ... Garcia , open the door !
Get out ! Out ! Out !
Come on ! Faster !
Move !
Move ! Keep going ! Move !
Get up ! Up ! Ma 'am ! Get up !
Get up ! Get up !
We are home . Are you okay ? Did they hurt you ?
- Letona ! Where is security ? - Dona Carmen , what happened ?
Nothing ! They didn 't steal anything , right ?
- - They hit me . - It was awful ! Those savages .
Tell dora to get my bath ready , please .
Dora is gone . - delia , then .
Everyone left ... - all of them ?
Ungrateful people .
We must call someone immediately .
Lots of people in my hometown want to work .
Then call them right now .
- I already did . They 're on their way . - Doctor , are you alright ?
Yes . Leave us , please . Make those people stop .
- Mom , what did they do to you ? - I got you all dirty !
- Did they hurt you ? - No , it 's not my blood .
- - Whose is it ? - Cow 's blood , I think .
Don 't be afraid . Everything 's going to be okay .
Mommy , I want to leave !
I don 't want to be here ! Let 's go home !
I 'm right here with you . Don 't be afraid .
I want to go !
Have you been here long ?
Yes , general .
Did you hear someone crying ?
Please , don 't expose yourself .
Alpha , agitator at twelve o 'clock . Verify perimeter four .
Good morning .
Are you alone ?
And the rest ?
They are afraid
there is a lot of work here . You won 't be able to handle it .
Who is it ? - the new maid !
Let her in ! Close the doors .
Valeriana , don 't open the door without my authorization .
I 'm sorry .
- Everything okay , officer ? - Yes , sir !
Come in . Wait there .
Stop here , please .
Extend your arms .
Turn around .
I 'm going to check your bag .
She 's clean .
- - Can I let my hair grow ? - Yes , honey .
And wear a dress like hers ?
May I show her around ?
Tomorrow . She must be tired .
I came here 27 years ago .
This is where we keep the food .
And here is our food .
Don 't worry . They buy us e verything .
These are our rooms .
This is the laundry room .
This is the ironing table .
The house is very brg .
Sometrmes it seems haunted
its better if you stay with me so you don 't get scared .
That 's all you brought with you ?
You 'll buy more , little by little .
Anyway , you ll ha ve a uniform here .
How is e veryone in town ?
They 're there .
If you want to clean yourself , there are showers here .
We want them alive ! We want them alive !
It 's an invasion . Will they ever leave us alone ?
It 's best if we don 't go out . It might be dangerous .
If you need anything , ask letona .
See , Sara ? Good news . You can skip school .
But I want to go to school .
It 's just a couple of days . I 'm also skipping the hospital .
It is not right for two women to live alone .
You should come live here . The house is big .
You would be protected by the guards .
Think about the girl .
Savages ! They are attacking us !
Sara ?
Get away from the window ! Follow me !
Come on ! Move !
- I 'm going to look for Sara . - Are you sure ?
Yes ! Stay with my parents ! Sara !
Sara !
- Call for backup . Call every unit . - Sara ?
- Yes ! Clear the area . - Sara !
Do as I say !
- Are you here , Sara ? - Arrest people if necessary .
I repeat . Arrest people if necessary !
Sara !
She 's not here . Please stay away from the windows .
I can 't find Sara .
The mob took her .
Don 't overreact .
- She has to be around here . - Let 's keep away from the large windows .
Use tear gas ! Now !
Sara ! - they threw more !
More ?
- - They broke windows ? - Yes .
Sara !
Se ven .
Ely / 71 .
Nine .
Ten .
E / e ven .
- - Twelve . - Sara !
Thirteen .
Fourteen .
Fifteen .
Sixteen .
- Se venteen . - Sa ra !
- - Erghteen . - Let go of her ! What are you doing ?
Let her go !
Mom , what 's with you ? I was about to get to 21 !
- What are you doing ? - Alma 's teaching me how to hold my breath .
We 'll practice in the pool later .
Both of you stay where we can see you . We were calling you . Didn 't you hear ?
Why are you always hiding ?
- - I 'm always looking for you . - Leave me alone !
You ha ve to stay alert all the time .
Now , come and help me . They threw many things .
Nobody quits ! Nobody forgets !
Enrique monte verde is a genocidal murderer !
You shouldn 't be here , Enrique ! They can throw rocks again .
Those people will drive me crazy .
Alma told me that there was a lot of water where she lived ,
and plants grew really fast .
You like Alma , don 't you ?
She has two kids .
Two kids ? So young .
Natives have many children so fast .
A boy and a girl .
Where does she leave them while she 's here ?
They 're already dead .
Valeriana , help me ! He is harassing me !
Don Enrique ! What are you doing here ? Get out of here !
Letona !
Help !
Get Don Enrique out of here !
For crying out loud , dad .
Please take her .
I can do it myself .
Don 't push yourself .
Give him oxygen , please .
Okay .
The floor was flooded .
I don 't want him sleeping in my room .
- - May I ? - Yes , please . Take him upstairs .
We should take him to the hospital .
That 's not Alzheimer 's . They won 't take him .
Enrique has always liked chasing women .
Particularly native women .
- I put the oxygen mask on Don Enrique . - - thank you .
- Good night . - Good night , valeriana .
All women drive Enrique crazy .
Don 't think about that . Don 't let it get to you .
I never thought that at this age I would still have to deal with this .
You better get some rest . I don 't want you to get sick .
You too , honey . Go to bed .
Did grandpa do something to Alma ?
Go to bed .
- Good night . - - night night , my love .
I 'll go get some water .
Come in .
- Excuse me . - Come in .
Alma , I want to apologize on my father 's behalf .
Please understand him . He 's under a lot of stress .
I promise it won 't happen again .
Starting tomorrow , do not wear your uniform .
It looks too tight on you . Wear your own gown .
- Good night . - Good night .
Open your shirt , please .
Breathe in .
One more time .
You have bronchial congestion .
We must treat your breathing deficiency .
With all those people out there , we can 't go out .
In the meantime , you must apologize to Alma .
Imagine the scandal if she reports you .
Apologize to her , please .
It 's just a formality . Do it for us .
I 've always sleepwalked .
You 've never sleepwalked .
My people , where are you ? Right here and being peaceful !
Remember ! We are not like them !
- Remember ! The people , united ... - Won 't be e ver defeated !
- The people , united ... - Won 't be e ver defeated !
The people , united , won 't be e ver defeated !
Nobody quits ! Nobody forgets !
Enrique monte verde is a genocidal murderer !
Check my eyes .
It looks like conjunctivitis .
I feel a lot of humidity in my bedroom .
Do you not find it weird
that your dad just showed up with valeriana one day ? Just like that ...
You were little , but she was also a child , barely older than Sara .
Those good deeds are not common in your dad .
God sends his toughest trials to his best servants ...
What are you trying to tell me ?
That surely valeriana is your half-sister .
Mom , please ! I need to relax .
I thought I was over that . Lately I cannot stop thinking about it .
Maybe it 's a blessing from heaven . What would I do without her ?
How did you meet valeriana ?
You already know how .
Why didn 't you like Sara 's father ?
It was he who didn 't like you . Don 't confuse things .
I love you , Princess .
I know .
- It 's beautiful . - Yes , it is .
Lets go !
- At your age it 's rather normal . - It was an accident .
I know .
There is no peace without justice !
You don 't have to wear it now if you don 't want to .
If you ever need them , you know where they are .
There is no peace without justice !
Sixteen .
Se venteen .
Erghteen .
Nineteen .
Twenty .
Twenty-one .
Twenty-two .
Twenty-three .
Twenty-four .
Twenty-five .
Twenty-six .
Twenty-se ven .
It can 't be .
Yes . Look . It does look like him .
Take a look again .
It does look like him .
Look at the others .
Look .
It 's him !
Yes , that one .
Sara , what are you two doing ?
- - Don 't play with that . - We 're not playing .
Take her somewhere else .
This historical phase of the country .
The phase of anticommunism , of the r 'nquisition ,
of the leaders that repressed and massacred ,
that ha ve committed economical and human genocide
under the argument of the fight against communism .
After a historical trial , hundreds of testimonials
and the annulment of the genocide verdict ,
the gap dividing public opinion r 'n Guatemala seems to grow wider .
Guatemala is tired of mournr 'ng its missing .
Here 's what you asked for .
Leave it there , please .
And I got this for Sara .
Thanks .
How risky is it to go out ?
This lock-up is making us sick .
Yes . I know .
Letona ?
Do you know about Sara 's father ?
Don 't you find it odd that he just disappeared all of a sudden ?
I have no access to that information .
Nobody knows what was he involved in .
It would be best if you stay away from those issues .
Excuse me .
Mine !
Need any help ? - no .
Where 's Sara ?
Watching TV .
Come , sit .
Did Sara see when my mom hit my dad ?
Was she scared ?
What was Sara 's dad like ?
Did Sara talk to you about him ?
She wants to know what he 's like , and where he is now .
The father of my children was very skinny .
He laughed a lot .
Where is he ?
I don 't know .
He left you ? - no .
And you ? Did he leave you ?
I never knew .
Excuse me .
Sara 's father was named Carlos .
He laughed a lot too .
Wind !
Fly !
Cold !
Rain !
Water !
Valeriana !
Coming !
Yes , sir ?
That 's what is killing me .
They 've cursed you .
Clean that up , please .
We must clean you up first .
All the hatred , all the talking about bad things must Lea ve .
Negative energy , lask you to leave this house for the sake of the family
ancestors , please help us understand who wants to harm us .
Protect our family from all e vil
make evil go away ...
We better go inside .
Let 's go .
Come , mom !
I talked to juana from our town ...
To get more help here .
But she said she doesn 't know you .
Where are you from ?
From the deepest part of the mountain .
Near the river .
Where the military camp was ?
I / ived there until the killings began .
How old are you ?
I don 't remember .
Come with me .
Sara ! Sara !
Dad !
Enrique , what are you doing ?
Enrique , stop !
That bitch !
She 's hiding under the water !
- Let go of the gun ! - It 's not my fault ! It 's hers !
It 's Sara ! It 's Sara !
That insurgent is under the water !
Don 't mess with my daughter !
Give me the gun . Go get my hospital kit .
Move ! Move !
Move away !
Valeriana , move away !
Walk ! - I am your father !
- Walk ! - Show respect !
Let go of me ! Let go !
Let go of me !
Everything that 's happening in this house is her fault .
- Don 't move ! I could hurt you . - Letona ! Letona !
Look . Look .
How did they get in ? Where are the guards ?
No guards can stop them .
Alma is crying for her kids .
She told me she 's known grandpa for a long time .
What else did she say ?
She asked me not to drown .
Valeriana , what 's happening ?
Grab all the candles you can and bring sugar .
Look .
Don 't look at them .
Hold hands .
Ica / I upon the four elements and the ancestors that protect us .
Spirits that torment us , speak to us through the fire .
What can we do for you ?
Spirits , go back to your slumber . There is nothing here for you .
We apologize if we did something wrong to you .
Forgive us .
Spirits , we respectfully ask you to leave us in peace .
If the general has a debt with you , please understand ...
We had nothing to do with it .
Ask the other spirits to show mercy upon us and go away .
You know its not fair for innocents to pay for the consequences .
Please don 't harm us ! Maybe we can help you ...
Sara , breathe . Open your eyes !
Sara , breathe ! Breathe !
Mom ! Mom , what 's happening to you ?
Mom !
General !
Tell me where the guerrillas are hiding .
I don 't understand what you 're saying .
My husband is not in the guerrilla , and neither are we .
Please Lea ve my children . Leave them out of this .
Either you tell me where they are , or I drown them .
I don 't know !
My chrldren ! My chrldren !
My children !
General .
Everyone cried for your land , Llorona
your land covered r 'n blood
everyone cried for your land , Llorona
sobs of wounded people , Llorona
and of silenced voices
I don 't know what the tlo wers hold Llorona
the flowers of burial grounds
for when the wind moves them , Llorona
it seems as though they are crying
you hide within the cornfields , Llorona
to avoid being hunted
lost souls wander , Llorona
and their warls are not forgotten
the chrldren dressed r 'n leaves , Llorona
their clothing turned to rags
you let out an agonizing scream , Llorona
that should break you into a thousand pieces
the lrght that used to shine , Llorona
Llorona , left you r 'n darkness
they snatched your dreams away , Llorona
but your strength remained
you came through the coffee plantations Llorona
suffering , demandr 'ng justice
the bullets srlenced the weeping , Llorona
since then you are not the same
Wash your suffering away , Llorona
Llorona with the blessed water from the river
wash your suffering away , Llorona
turn your anguish into peace , Llorona
and turn the dawn r 'nto dew
and turn the dawn
lnto dew